Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 10: Prenatal Care.
Prenatal Care In The United States Diagnosis Of Pregnancy Initial Prenatal Evaluation Subsequent Prenatal Visits Nutritional Counseling Common Concerns References The American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) define prenatal care as “A comprehensive antepartum program involves a coordinated approach to medical care, continuous risk assessment, and psychosocial support that optimally begins before pregnancy and extends throughout the
postpartum and interpregnancy period.
As promulgated by John Ballantyne, such care has been a bedrock to improve pregnancy outcomes for more than 100 years .
Prenatal Care In The United States.
Almost a century after its introduction, prenatal care has become one of the most frequently used health services in the United States.
According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), only 1.6 percent of women who gave birth in 2016 received no prenatal care .
African-American and Hispanic women have high rates of inadequate or no prenatal care that reach 10 and 7.7 percent, respectively.
This figure is greater for adolescents, particularly those younger than 15 years, compared with older age groups.
These data highlight areas of potential improvement by the health-care system.
# Prenatal Care Effectiveness.
Care designed during the early 1900s focused on lowering the extremely high maternal mortality rate.
Prenatal care undoubtedly contributed to the dramatic decline in maternal deaths from 690 per 100,000 births in 1920 to 50 per 100,000 by 1955 .
Data from 1998 to 2005 from the Pregnancy Mortality Surveillance System identified a fivefold increased risk for maternal death in women who received no prenatal care .
Goldenberg and McClure (2018) have emphasized the importance of prenatal care to reduce stillbirth rates as well.
In a study of almost 29 million births, the risk for preterm birth, stillbirth, early and late neonatal death, and infant death rose linearly with decreasing prenatal care utilization .
Similarly, from Parkland Hospital, Leveno and associates (2009) found that a significant decline in preterm births correlated closely with any use of prenatal care by medically indigent women.
And in women with diabetes, adherence to prenatal care resulted in lower rates of neonatal admissions to the intensive care unit .
Group prenatal care is acceptable and effective .
Ickovics and coworkers (2016) compared this with individual prenatal care.
Group care provided traditional pregnancy surveillance in a group setting with special focus on support, education, and active health-care participation.
Women enrolled in group care had significantly better pregnancy outcomes.
Carter and colleagues (2017) cited similar results.
Childbirth education classes are also reported to result in better pregnancy outcomes .
Pregnancy in adolescents carries special risk, and guidelines have been developed that focus on this age group .
Diagnosis Of Pregnancy.
Pregnancy is usually identified when a woman presents with symptoms and possibly a positive home urine pregnancy test result.
Typically, these women receive confirmatory testing of urine or blood for human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG).
Further, presumptive signs or diagnostic findings of pregnancy may be found during the clinical examination.
Sonography is often used, especially if miscarriage or ectopic pregnancy is a concern.
# Symptoms and Signs.
Amenorrhea in a healthy reproductive-aged woman who previously has experienced spontaneous, cyclical, predictable menses is highly suggestive of pregnancy.
Menstrual cycles vary appreciably in length among women and even in the same woman .
Thus, amenorrhea is not a reliable pregnancy indicator until 10 or more days have passed after expected menses.
Occasionally, uterine bleeding that mimics menstruation is noted after conception.
During the first month of pregnancy, these episodes are likely the consequence of blastocyst implantation.
Still, first-trimester bleeding should prompt
evaluation for an abnormal pregnancy.
Of other symptoms, maternal perception of fetal movement depends on factors such as parity and habitus.
In general, after a first successful pregnancy, a woman may first perceive fetal movements between 16 and 18 weeks’ gestation.
A primigravida may not appreciate fetal movements until approximately 2 weeks later.
At about 20 weeks, depending on maternal habitus, an examiner can begin to detect fetal movements.
Of pregnancy signs, changes in the lower reproductive tract, uterus, and breasts develop early.
# Pregnancy Tests.
Detection of hCG in maternal blood and urine is the basis for endocrine assays of pregnancy.
Syncytiotrophoblast produces hCG in amounts that increase exponentially during the first trimester.
hCG and luteinizing hormone (LH) share the same receptor in tissues.
Thus, a main function of hCG is to prevent involution of the corpus luteum, which is the principal site of progesterone formation during the first 6 weeks of pregnancy.
With a sensitive test, the hormone can be detected in maternal serum or urine by 8 to 9 days after ovulation.
The doubling time of serum hCG concentration is 1.4 to 2.0 days.
As shown in Figure 10-1, serum levels range widely and increase from the day of implantation.
Lower levels of hCG rise more rapidly than higher levels .
Peak hCG levels are reached at 60 to 70 days.
Thereafter, the concentration declines slowly to a plateau at approximately 16 weeks’ gestation.
Figure 10-1.
Mean concentration (95% CI) of human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) in serum of women throughout normal pregnancy.
Measurement of hCG This hormone is a glycoprotein with high carbohydrate content.
The general structure of hCG is a heterodimer composed of two dissimilar subunits, designated α and β, which are noncovalently linked.
The α-subunit is identical to those of LH, follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH), and thyroidstimulating hormone (TSH), but the β-subunit is structurally distinct.
Thus, antibodies were developed with high specificity for the hCG β-subunit.
This specificity allows its detection, and numerous commercial immunoassays are available for measuring serum and urine hCG levels.
Each immunoassay detects a slightly different mixture of hCG variants, its free subunits, or its metabolites—however, all are appropriate for pregnancy testing .
Depending on the assay used, the sensitivity for the laboratory detection limit of hCG in serum is 1.0 mIU/mL or even lower.
False-positive hCG test results are rare.
A few women have circulating serum factors that may bind erroneously with the test antibody directed to hCG in a given assay.
The most common factors are heterophilic antibodies.
These are produced by an individual and bind to the animal-derived test antibodies used in a given immunoassay.
Thus, women who have worked closely with animals are more likely to develop these antibodies, and alternative laboratory techniques are available .
Elevated hCG levels may also reflect molar pregnancy and its associated neoplasms .
Other rare causes of positive assays without pregnancy are (1) exogenous hCG injection used for weight loss, (2) renal failure with impaired hCG clearance, (3) physiological pituitary hCG, and (4) hCG-producing tumors that most commonly originate from gastrointestinal sites, ovary, bladder, or lung .
Home Pregnancy Tests More than 60 different types of over-the-counter pregnancy test kits are available in the United States .
Unfortunately, many of these are not as accurate as advertised .
For example, Cole and associates (2011) found that a detection limit of 12.5 mIU/mL would be required to diagnose 95 percent of pregnancies at the time of missed menses.
However, they reported that only one brand had this degree of sensitivity.
Two other brands gave false-positive or invalid results.
In fact, with an hCG concentration of 100 mIU/mL, clearly positive results were displayed by only 44 percent of brands.
Accordingly, only approximately 15 percent of pregnancies could be diagnosed at the time of the missed menses.
Some manufacturers of
even newer home urine assays claim >99-percent accuracy for tests done on the day of—and some up to 4 days before—the expected day of menses.
Again, careful analysis suggests that these assays are often not as sensitive as advertised.
# Sonographic Recognition of Pregnancy.
Transvaginal sonography is commonly used to accurately establish gestational age and confirm pregnancy location.
A gestational sac is the first sonographic evidence of pregnancy, and it may be seen with transvaginal sonography by 4 to 5 weeks’ gestation.
It should not be confused with a pseudogestational sac.
The latter, or pseudosac, is a fluid collection within the endometrial cavity, which can occur in the setting of ectopic pregnancy (Fig. 12-3, p. 223).
Further evaluation may be warranted if this is the only sonographic finding, particularly in a woman with pain or bleeding.
A normal gestational sac implants eccentrically in the endometrium, whereas a pseudosac is seen in the midline of the endometrial cavity.
Other potential indicators of early intrauterine pregnancy are an anechoic center surrounded by a single echogenic rim—the intradecidual sign—or two concentric echogenic rings surrounding the gestational sac—the double decidual sign .
If sonography yields equivocal findings, the term pregnancy of unknown location (PUL) is applied .
In these cases, serial serum hCG levels and transvaginal sonography can help differentiate a normal intrauterine pregnancy from an extrauterine pregnancy or an early miscarriage .
Figure 10-2.
Transvaginal sonogram of a first-trimester intrauterine pregnancy.
The double decidual sign is noted surrounding the gestational sac and is defined by the decidua parietalis (white asterisk) and the decidua capsularis (yellow asterisk).
The arrow notes the yolk sac, and the crown-rump length of the embryo is marked with measuring calipers.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Elysia Moschos.
If the yolk sac—a brightly echogenic ring with an anechoic center—is seen within the gestational sac, an intrauterine location for the pregnancy is confirmed.
The yolk sac can normally be seen by the middle of the fifth week.
As shown in Figure 10-2, after 6 weeks, an embryo is seen as a linear structure immediately adjacent to the yolk sac.
Cardiac motion is typically noted at this point.
Initial Prenatal Evaluation.
Prenatal care is ideally initiated early.
Major goals are to (1) define the health status of the mother and fetus, (2) estimate the gestational age, and (3) initiate a plan for continued obstetrical care.
Typical components of the initial visit are summarized in Table 10-1.
Subsequent care may range from relatively infrequent routine visits to prompt hospitalization because of serious maternal or fetal disease.
Table 10-1.
Typical Components of Routine Prenatal Care # Prenatal Record.
Use of a standardized record within a perinatal health-care system greatly aids antepartum and intrapartum management.
Standardizing documentation allows communication and care continuity between providers and enables objective measures of care quality to be evaluated over time and across different clinical settings .
A prototype is provided by the American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) in their Guidelines for Perinatal Care, 8th edition.
Definitions Several definitions are pertinent to establishment of an accurate prenatal record.
1. Nulligravida—a woman who currently is not pregnant and has never been pregnant.
2. Gravida—a woman who currently is pregnant or has been in the past, irrespective of the pregnancy outcome.
With the establishment of the first pregnancy, she becomes a primigravida, and with successive pregnancies, a multigravida.
3. Nullipara—a woman who has never completed a pregnancy beyond 20 weeks’ gestation.
She may not have been pregnant or may have had a spontaneous or elective abortion(s) or an ectopic pregnancy.
4. Primipara—a woman who has been delivered only once of a fetus or fetuses born alive or dead with an estimated gestation
duration of 20 or more weeks.
In the past, a 500-g birthweight threshold was used to define parity.
This threshold is now controversial.
Namely, many states still use this weight to differentiate a stillborn fetus from an abortus, but the survival of neonates with birthweights <500 g is no longer uncommon .
5. Multipara—a woman who has completed two or more pregnancies with gestational ages at least 20 weeks.
Parity is determined by the number of pregnancies reaching 20 weeks.
It is not increased to a higher number if multiples are delivered in a given pregnancy.
Moreover, stillbirth does not lower this number.
In some locales, the obstetrical history is summarized by a series of digits connected by dashes.
These refer to the number of term newborns, preterm neonates, abortuses younger than 20 weeks, and children currently alive.
For example, a woman who is para 2–1–0–3 has had two term deliveries, one preterm delivery, no abortuses, and has three living children.
Because these are nonconventional, it is helpful to specify the outcome of any pregnancy that did not end normally.
Normal Pregnancy Duration The normal duration of pregnancy calculated from the first day of the last normal menstrual period is very close to 280 days or 40 weeks.
A quick estimate of a pregnancy due date based on menstrual data can be made as follows: add 7 days to the first day of the last period and subtract 3 months.
For example, if the first day of the last menses was October 5, the due date is 10-05 minus 3 (months) plus 7 (days) = 7–12 or July 12 of the following year.
This calculation is the Naegele rule.
However, menstrual cycle length varies among women and renders many of these calculations inaccurate.
This, combined with the frequent use of first-trimester sonography, has changed the method of determining an accurate gestational age.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017e), the American Institute of Ultrasound in Medicine, and the Society for MaternalFetal Medicine have emphasized that first-trimester ultrasound is the most accurate method to establish or reaffirm gestational age.
For pregnancies conceived by assisted reproductive technologies, embryo age or transfer date is used to assign gestational age.
If available, the gestational ages calculated from the last menstrual period and from first-trimester ultrasound are compared, and this estimated date of delivery is recorded.
Reconciling any discordance between these two values is discussed in Chapter 14 (p. 248).
Trimesters It has become customary to divide pregnancy into three equal epochs or trimesters of approximately 3 calendar months.
More recently a “fourth trimester” has been recognized to emphasize the need for comprehensive postpartum care .
This is discussed in Chapter 36 (p. 634).
Historically, the first trimester extends through completion of 14 weeks, the second through 28 weeks, and the third through 42 weeks.
The fourth is the 12 weeks after delivery.
Thus, prenatally, there are three periods of 14 weeks each.
Certain major obstetrical problems tend to cluster in each of these three time periods.
For example, most spontaneous abortions take place during the first trimester, whereas most women with hypertensive disorders due to pregnancy are diagnosed during the third trimester.
In modern obstetrics, the clinical use of trimesters to describe a specific pregnancy is imprecise.
For example, it is inappropriate in cases of uterine hemorrhage to categorize the problem temporally as “third-trimester bleeding.
Appropriate management for the mother and her fetus will vary remarkably depending on whether bleeding begins early or late in the third trimester .
Because precise knowledge of fetal age is imperative for obstetrical management, the clinically appropriate unit is weeks of gestation completed.
Clinicians designate gestational age using completed weeks and days.
For example, 334/7 weeks or 33 + 4 describes pregnancy duration of 33 completed weeks and 4 days.
Previous and Current Health Status As elsewhere in medicine,
history-taking begins with queries concerning medical or surgical disorders.
Detailed information regarding previous pregnancies is essential, as many obstetrical complications tend to recur in subsequent pregnancies.
The menstrual and contraceptive histories also are important.
As noted earlier, gestational age may be less accurate for those with irregular menses.
Moreover, some methods of birth control favor ectopic implantation following method failure .
Psychosocial Screening.
The American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) define psychosocial issues as nonbiomedical factors that affect mental and physical well-being.
Women should be screened regardless of social status, education level, race, or ethnicity.
Such screening should seek barriers to care, communication obstacles, nutritional status, unstable housing, desire for pregnancy, safety concerns that include intimate-partner violence, depression, stress, and use of substances such as tobacco, alcohol, and illicit drugs.
This screening is performed on a regular basis, at least once per trimester, to identify important issues and reduce adverse pregnancy outcomes.
Coker and colleagues (2012) compared pregnancy outcomes in women before and after implementation of a universal psychosocial screening program and found that screened women were less likely to have preterm or low-birthweight newborns, as well as other adverse outcomes.
Specific screens for depression are presented in Chapter 64 (p. 1143).
Cigarette Smoking.
These data are included on the birth certificate, and the number of pregnant women who smoke continues to decline.
From 2000 to 2010, the prevalences were 12 to 13 percent .
By 2016, the incidence was 7.2 percent according to the National Center for Health Statistics .
Concurrent with the decline in cigarette use, there has been an increase in electronic cigarettes/vaping with a reported prevalence of 0.6 to 15 percent .
In a survey of more than 3000 mothers in Oklahoma and Texas, 7 percent reported using electronic vapor products prior to conception and in the postpartum period.
Of these women, according to the CDC, 1.4 percent used them during the last 3 months of pregnancy .
According to the American Society for Reproductive Medicine (2018), smoking is associated with subfertility.
Higher rates of miscarriage, stillbirth, low birthweight, and preterm delivery also are linked to smoking during pregnancy (Dahlin, 2016; Luke, 2018; Tong, 2013).
Compared with nonsmokers, risks of placenta previa, placental abruption, and premature membrane rupture are increased twofold.
Potential teratogenic effects are reviewed in Chapter 8 (p. 156).
Thus, the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force recommends that clinicians offer counseling and effective intervention options to pregnant smokers at the first and subsequent prenatal visits .
Although benefits are greatest if smoking ceases early in pregnancy or preferably preconceptionally, quitting at any stage of pregnancy can improve perinatal outcomes .
Compared with simple counseling to quit, person-to-person psychosocial interventions are significantly more successful in achieving smoking abstinence in pregnancy .
One example is a brief counseling session covering the “5As” of smoking cessation .
This approach can be accomplished in 15 minutes or less and is effective when initiated by health-care providers .
Table 10-2.
Five A’s of Smoking Cessation Behavioral interventions and nicotine replacement products are successful in reducing smoking rates .
However, nicotine replacement has not been sufficiently evaluated to determine its effectiveness and safety in pregnancy.
Trials evaluating such therapy have yielded conflicting evidence (Coleman, 2015; Spindel, 2016).
Two randomized trials also produced inconclusive results.
In the Smoking and Nicotine in Pregnancy (SNAP) trial, Cooper and associates (2014) reported that a temporary cessation of smoking may have been associated with improved infant development.
In the Study of Nicotine Patch in Pregnancy
SNIPP) trial, no differences in smoking cessation rates or birthweights were found .
Similar preliminary results were reported for sustainedrelease bupropion .
Olson and colleagues (2019) reported that financial incentives were helpful to encourage smoking cessation.
Because of limited available evidence to support pharmacotherapy for smoking cessation in pregnancy, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020b) recommends that if nicotine replacement therapy is used, it should be done with close supervision and after careful consideration of the risks of smoking versus nicotine replacement.
Alcohol.
Ethyl alcohol or ethanol is a potent teratogen that causes the fetal alcohol spectrum disorders.
Fetal alcohol syndrome, the most severe form of these disorders, is characterized by growth restriction, facial abnormalities, and central nervous system dysfunction.
The estimated prevalence of these disorders is 11 to 50 per 1000 .
As discussed in Chapter 8 (p. 150), women who are pregnant or considering pregnancy should abstain from drinking any alcoholic beverages .
The CDC analyzed data from the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System from 2015 to 2017 and estimated that 12 percent of pregnant women used alcohol .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2021a) in collaboration with the CDC has developed the Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorders (FASD) Prevention Program, which provides resources for providers and is available at www.acog.org/alcohol.
Illicit Drugs.
An estimated 10 percent of fetuses are exposed to one or more illicit drugs.
Agents may include heroin and other opiates, cocaine, amphetamines, barbiturates, and marijuana .
As discussed in Chapter 8 (p. 157), chronic use of large quantities is harmful to the fetus .
Well-documented sequelae include fetal-growth restriction, low birthweight, and drug withdrawal soon after birth.
Adverse effects of marijuana are less convincing.
Women who use such drugs frequently do not seek prenatal care, which in itself is associated with risks for preterm and low-birthweight neonates .
For women who abuse heroin, methadone maintenance can be initiated within a registered methadone treatment program to reduce complications of illicit opioid use and narcotic withdrawal, to encourage prenatal care, and to avoid drug culture risks .
Available programs can be found through the treatment locator of the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration at www.samhsa.gov.
Methadone dosages usually are initiated at 10 to 30 mg orally daily and titrated as needed.
In some women, careful methadone taper may be an appropriate option .
Buprenorphine alone or in combination with naloxone also may be offered and managed by physicians with specific credentialing.
These therapeutic options are considered in greater detail in Chapter 64 (p. 1150).
Intimate-Partner Violence.
This term refers to a pattern of assault and coercive behavior that may include physical injury, psychological abuse, sexual assault, progressive isolation, stalking, deprivation, intimidation, and reproductive coercion .
Such violence is recognized as a major public health problem.
Unfortunately, most abused women continue to be victimized during pregnancy.
With the possible exception of preeclampsia, intimate-partner violence (IPV) is more prevalent than any major medical condition detectable through routine prenatal screening .
The estimated prevalence during pregnancy lies between 4 and 8 percent.
IPV is associated with an increased risk of several adverse perinatal outcomes that include preterm delivery, fetal-growth restriction, and perinatal death .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019c) has provided methods for IPV screening and recommends their use at the first prenatal visit, again at least once per trimester, and again at the postpartum visit.
Such screening should be done privately and away from family members and friends.
Patient self-administered or computerized screenings appear to be as effective for disclosure as clinician-directed
interviews (Ahmad, 2009; Chen, 2007).
Physicians should be familiar with state laws that may require reporting of IPV.
Coordination with social services can be invaluable in these cases.
The National Domestic Violence Hotline (1–800– 799-SAFE [7233]) is a nonprofit telephone referral service that provides individualized information regarding city-specific shelter locations, counseling resources, and legal advocacy.
# Clinical Evaluation.
Thorough, general physical and pelvic examinations should be completed at the initial prenatal encounter.
The cervix is visualized using a speculum lubricated with warm water or water-based lubricant gel.
Bluish-red passive hyperemia of the cervix is characteristic, but not diagnostic, of pregnancy.
Dilated, occluded cervical glands bulging beneath the ectocervical mucosa— nabothian cysts—may be prominent.
The cervix is not normally dilated except at the external os.
To identify cytological abnormalities, a Pap test is performed according to current guidelines noted in Chapter 66 (p. 1164).
Specimens for identification of Chlamydia trachomatis and Neisseria gonorrhoeae are obtained when indicated (p. 181).
Bimanual examination is completed by palpation.
Special attention is given to the consistency, length, and dilation of the cervix; to uterine and adnexal size; to the bony pelvic architecture; and to any vaginal or perineal anomalies.
Often, later in pregnancy, fetal presentation also can be determined.
Lesions of the cervix, vagina, or vulva are further evaluated as needed by colposcopy, biopsy, or culture.
The perianal region is inspected, and digital rectal examination is performed as required for complaints of rectal pain, bleeding, or mass.
Gestational Age Assessment Precise knowledge of gestational age is essential for prenatal care, because several pregnancy complications may develop and optimal treatment will depend on fetal age.
Menstrual history is best confirmed by first-trimester sonography .
That said, gestational age can also be estimated with considerable precision by a carefully performed clinical uterine size examination that is coupled with last menstrual period dating.
Uterine size similar to a small orange roughly correlates with a 6-week gestation; a large orange, with an 8-week pregnancy; and a grapefruit, with one at 12 weeks .
# Laboratory Tests.
Recommended routine tests at the first prenatal encounter are listed in Table 10-1.
Initial blood tests include a complete blood count, a determination of blood type and Rh status, and an antibody screen.
The Institute of Medicine recommends universal human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) testing as a routine part of prenatal care.
This testing is explained to the patient, who may decline.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018j) continues to support this practice.
If a woman declines, this is recorded in the prenatal record.
All pregnant women are screened also for hepatitis B virus infection, syphilis, and immunity to rubella at the initial visit.
Based on their prospective investigation of 1000 women, Murray and coworkers (2002) concluded that in the absence of hypertension, routine urinalysis beyond the first prenatal visit was unnecessary.
A urine culture is recommended by most, because treating bacteriuria significantly reduces the likelihood of developing symptomatic urinary tract infections in pregnancy .
Cervical Infections C trachomatis is isolated from the cervix in 2 to 13 percent of pregnant women.
The American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) recommend that all women be screened for chlamydia during the first prenatal visit, with additional thirdtrimester testing for those at increased risk.
Risk factors include unmarried status, recent change in sexual partner or multiple concurrent partners, age younger than 25 years, inner-city residence, history or presence of other sexually transmitted diseases, and little or no prenatal care.
For those testing positive, treatment described in Chapter 68 (p. 1212) is followed by a
second testing—a test of cure—3 to 4 weeks after treatment completion.
N gonorrhoeae typically causes cervicitis or urethritis in pregnancy.
Infrequently, it may also cause septic arthritis .
Risk factors for gonorrhea are similar to those for chlamydial infection.
The American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) recommend that pregnant women with risk factors or those living in an area of high N gonorrhoeae prevalence be screened at the initial prenatal visit and again in the third trimester.
Treatment is given for gonorrhea and simultaneously for possible coexisting chlamydial infection .
Test of cure is recommended following treatment.
# Pregnancy Risk Assessment.
Many factors can adversely affect maternal and fetal well-being.
Some are evident at conception, but many become apparent during the course of pregnancy.
The designation of “high-risk pregnancy” is overly vague for an individual woman and is best avoided if a more specific diagnosis can be assigned.
Some common risk factors for which consultation is recommended by the American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) are shown in Table 10-3.
Some conditions may require the involvement of a maternal-fetal medicine specialist, geneticist, neonatologist, anesthesiologist, cardiologist, or other specialist.
Table 10-3.
Conditions for Which Maternal-Fetal Medicine Consultation May Be Beneficial Subsequent Prenatal Visits.
These are traditionally scheduled at 4-week intervals until 28 weeks, then every 2 weeks until 36 weeks, and weekly thereafter.
Women with complicated pregnancies—for example, with twins or diabetes—often require return visits at 1- to 2-week intervals .
In 1986, the Department of Health and Human Services convened an expert panel to review the content of prenatal care.
This report was subsequently reevaluated and revised in 2005 .
The panel recommended, among other things, early and continuing risk assessment that is patient specific.
It also endorsed flexibility in clinical visit spacing; health promotion and education, including preconceptional care; medical and psychosocial interventions; standardized documentation; and expanded prenatal care objectives that include family health up to 1 year after birth.
The World Health Organization conducted a multicenter randomized trial with almost 25,000 women that compared routine prenatal care with an experimental model designed to minimize visits .
In the new model, women were seen once in the first trimester and screened for certain risks.
Those without anticipated complications—80 percent of those screened—were seen again at 26, 32, and 38 weeks.
Compared with routine prenatal care, which required a median of eight visits, the new model required a median of only five.
No disadvantages were attributed to the regimen with fewer visits, and these findings are consistent with other randomized trials.
# Prenatal Surveillance.
At each return visit, the well-being of mother and fetus are assessed (see Table 10-1.
Fetal heart rate, growth, and activity are evaluated.
Maternal blood pressure and weight and their extent of change are assessed.
Symptoms such as abdominal pain, nausea and vomiting, bleeding, vaginal fluid leakage, headache, altered vision, and dysuria are sought.
After 20 weeks’ gestation, uterine examination measures size from the symphysis to the fundus with a traditional tape measure.
In late pregnancy, vaginal examination often provides valuable information.
This may include confirmation of the presenting part and its station, clinical estimation of pelvic capacity and configuration, fetal ballottement as a reflection of sufficient amnionic fluid volume, and cervical consistency, effacement, and dilation .
Fundal Height Between 20 and 34 weeks’ gestation, the height of the uterine fundus measured in centimeters correlates closely with gestational age in weeks.
This measurement is used to monitor fetal growth and amnionic fluid volume.
It is measured along the
abdominal wall from the top of the symphysis pubis to the top of the fundus.
Importantly, the bladder must be emptied before fundal measurement.
Obesity or the presence of uterine masses such as leiomyomas also may limit fundal height measurement accuracy.
Moreover, using fundal height alone, fetal-growth restriction may be undiagnosed in up to a third of cases (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2021b; Haragan, 2015).
Fetal Heart Sounds Instruments incorporating Doppler ultrasound are usually used to easily detect fetal heart action, and in the absence of maternal obesity, heart sounds are almost always detectable by 10 weeks with such instruments .
The fetal heart rate ranges from 110 to 160 beats per minute and is typically heard as a double sound.
Using a standard nonamplified stethoscope, the fetal heart is audible by 20 weeks in 80 percent of women, and by 22 weeks, heart sounds are expected to be heard in all .
Because the fetus moves freely in amnionic fluid, the site on the maternal abdomen where fetal heart sounds can be heard best will vary.
Additionally, with ultrasonic auscultation, one may hear the funic souffle, which is a sharp, whistling sound that is synchronous with the fetal pulse.
It is caused by the rush of blood through the umbilical arteries and may not be heard consistently.
In contrast, the uterine souffle is a soft, blowing sound that is synchronous with the maternal pulse.
It is produced by the passage of blood through the dilated uterine vessels and is heard most distinctly near the lower portion of the uterus.
Sonography Ultrasound imaging provides invaluable information regarding fetal anatomy, growth, and well-being.
As such, it is recommended that all pregnant women be offered at least one prenatal sonographic examination .
Continuing trends suggest that the number of these examinations performed per pregnancy is increasing.
Data from commercial insurance plans indicate that even low-risk pregnancies receive an average of 4 to 5 ultrasound examinations (O’Keeffe, 2013).
Sonography should be performed only for valid medical indications.
Additionally, needed information is obtained using the lowest possible ultrasound exposure settings, which is the as low as reasonably achievable (ALARA) principle .
# Subsequent Laboratory Tests.
If initial results were normal, most tests need not be repeated.
Hematocrit or hemoglobin determination, along with serology for syphilis if it is prevalent in the population, is repeated at 28 to 32 weeks (Hollier, 2003; Kiss, 2004).
For women at increased risk for HIV acquisition during pregnancy, repeat testing is recommended in the third trimester, preferably before 36 weeks .
Similarly, women who engage in behaviors that place them at high risk for hepatitis B virus infection are retested at the time of delivery.
Women who are D (Rh) negative and are unsensitized should have an antibody screening test repeated at 28 to 29 weeks.
Anti-D immunoglobulin is given if they remain unsensitized .
Group B Streptococcal Infection The CDC (2010b) recommends that vaginal and rectal group B streptococcal (GBS) cultures be obtained in all women between 35 and 37 weeks’ gestation, and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020f) endorses this recommendation.
Intrapartum antimicrobial prophylaxis is provided to those whose culture results are positive.
Women with GBS bacteriuria, preterm labor, or a previous infant with invasive disease are given empirical intrapartum prophylaxis.
Trials are in progress to test an investigational vaccine .
These infections are described further in Chapter 67 (p. 1194).
Gestational Diabetes All pregnant women are screened for gestational diabetes mellitus, whether by history, clinical factors, or routine laboratory testing.
Although laboratory testing between 24 and 28 weeks’ gestation is the most sensitive approach, there may be women at low risk who are less likely to benefit from testing .
Gestational diabetes is discussed in Chapter 60 (p. 1079).
Genetic Screening Serum screening for fetal
aneuploidy is routinely offered to all pregnant women—in the first trimester at 10 to 14 weeks, in the second trimester at 15 to 20 weeks, or as cell-free DNA screening at any point after 10 weeks .
Additionally, the College recommends that both cystic fibrosis carrier screening and screening for spinal muscular atrophy should be offered to all women considering pregnancy or who are currently pregnant, provided that carrier or disease status is not already known .
Historically, carrier screening for selected genetic abnormalities was offered only to women at increased risk based on ethnic or racial background.
One example is screening for Tay-Sachs disease in those of Ashkenazi Jewish descent.
However, given our increasingly diverse, multiethnic society, previous assumptions about carrier risk may no longer apply.
Although ethnicity-specific carrier screening remains an option, providers should also consider panethnic and expanded carrier screening strategies .
These are discussed further in Chapter 17 (p. 342).
All genetic screening is optional, and ideally, genetic carrier screening and counseling should be performed before pregnancy.
Neural-Tube Defects Traditionally, screening for neural-tube defects has been performed as part of second-trimester aneuploidy screening.
An elevation of maternal serum alpha-fetoprotein (MSAFP) levels then prompted additional evaluation with ultrasound and/or amniocentesis.
With the advent of other screening modalities for aneuploidy, second-trimester MSAFP testing is less frequently obtained.
For example, the expansion of second-trimester fetal anatomical surveillance has been used to screen and identify neural-tube defects .
Nutritional Counseling.
# Weight Gain Recommendations.
In 2009, the Institute of Medicine and National Research Council revised guidelines for weight gain in pregnancy and continued to stratify suggested weight gain ranges based on prepregnancy body mass index (BMI) .
The same recommendations apply to women in all age, race, and ethnic groups.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018n) endorses these measures.
Table 10-4.
Recommendations for Total and Rate of Weight Gain During Pregnancy When the initial Institute of Medicine guidelines were formulated, concern focused on low-birthweight newborns.
However, current emphasis is directed to the obesity epidemic.
The specific and relatively narrow range of recommended weight gains for obese women emphasizes the renewed interest in lower weight gains during pregnancy.
Obesity is associated with significantly greater risks for gestational hypertension, preeclampsia, gestational diabetes, macrosomia, cesarean delivery, and other complications .
The risk appears proportionate to prenatal weight gain.
In a Maternal-Fetal Medicine Units Network cohort of more than 29,000 pregnant women, 51 percent had weight gain above and 21 percent below the guidelines .
Those with excessive weight gain had higher rates of hypertension and cesarean delivery.
This risk is even greater in chronically hypertensive women .
Conversely, among 100,000 women with normal prepregnancy BMI, DeVader and colleagues (2007) found that those who gained <25 lb during pregnancy had a lower risk for preeclampsia, failed induction, cephalopelvic disproportion, cesarean delivery, and large-for-gestational age neonates.
This cohort, however, had an increased risk for small-for-gestational age newborns.
# Severe Undernutrition.
Meaningful studies of nutrition in human pregnancy are exceedingly difficult to design because experimental dietary deficiency is not ethical.
In those instances in which severe nutritional deficiencies have been induced as a consequence of social, economic, or political disaster, coincidental events have often created many variables, the effects of which are not amenable to quantification.
Some past experiences suggest, however, that in otherwise healthy women, a state of near starvation is required to establish clear differences in pregnancy outcome.
These are discussed in Chapter 47 (p. 827).
# Weight
Retention After Pregnancy.
Not all the weight gained during pregnancy is lost during and immediately after delivery.
Schauberger and coworkers (1992) studied prenatal and postpartum weights in 795 women.
Their average weight gain was 28.6 lb or 12.9 kg.
As shown in Figure 10-3, most maternal weight loss was at delivery —approximately 12 lb or 5.4 kg—and in the ensuing 2 weeks— approximately 9 lb or 4 kg.
An additional 5.5 lb or 2.5 kg was lost between 2 weeks and 6 months postpartum.
Thus, average retained pregnancy weight was 2.1 lb or 1 kg.
Excessive weight gain is manifest by accrual of fat and may be partially retained as long-term fat (Berggren, 2016; Widen, 2015).
Overall, the more weight that was gained during pregnancy, the more that was lost postpartum.
And breastfeeding duration is inversely related to weight retention .
Figure 10-3.
Cumulative weight loss from last antepartum visit to 6 months postpartum.
On average, 1 kg will be retained after pregnancy.
Significantly different from 2-week weight loss; Significantly different from 6-week weight loss.
Redrawn with permission from Schauberger CW, Rooney BL, Brimer LM: Factors that influence weight loss in the puerperium.
Obstet Gynecol 79:424, 1992.
# Dietary Reference Intakes—Recommended Allowances.
Periodically, the Institute of Medicine (2006, 2011) publishes recommended dietary allowances, including those for pregnant or lactating women.
Some of its latest recommendations are summarized in Table 10-5.
Certain prenatal vitamin–mineral supplements may lead to intakes well in excess of the recommended allowances.
Moreover, the use of excessive supplements, which often are self-prescribed, has led to concern regarding nutrient toxicities during pregnancy.
Those with potentially toxic effects include iron, zinc, selenium, and vitamins A, B6, C, and D. Table 10-5.
Recommended Daily Dietary Allowances for Pregnant and Lactating Women # Calories.
As shown in Figure 10-4, pregnancy requires an additional 80,000 kcal, mostly during the last 20 weeks.
To meet this demand, a caloric increase of 100 to 300 kcal/d is recommended during pregnancy .
This greater intake, however, should not be divided equally during the course of pregnancy.
The Institute of Medicine (2006) recommends adding 0, 340, and 452 kcal/d to the estimated nonpregnant energy requirements in the first, second, and third trimesters, respectively.
The addition of 1000 kcal/d or more results in fat accrual .
Figure 10-4.
Cumulative kilocalories required for pregnancy.
Redrawn with permission from Chamberlain G, Broughton-Pipkin F [eds]: Clinical Physiology in Obstetrics, 3rd ed. Oxford, Blackwell Science, 1998.
Whenever caloric intake is inadequate, protein is metabolized rather than being spared for its vital role in fetal growth and development.
Total physiological requirements during pregnancy are not necessarily the sum of ordinary nonpregnant requirements plus those specific to pregnancy.
For example, the additional energy required during pregnancy may be compensated in whole or in part by reduced physical activity .
# Protein.
Protein requirements rise to meet the demands for growth and remodeling of the fetus, placenta, uterus, and breasts, and for the expanded maternal blood volume .
During the second half of pregnancy, approximately 1000 g of protein are deposited, amounting to 5 to 6 g/d .
To accomplish this, protein intake that approximates 1 g/kg/d is recommended .
Data suggest this should be doubled in late gestation .
Most amino-acid levels in maternal plasma fall markedly, including ornithine, glycine, taurine, and proline .
Exceptions during pregnancy are glutamic acid and alanine, the concentrations of which rise.
Preferably, most protein is supplied from animal sources, such as meat, milk, eggs, cheese, poultry, and fish.
These furnish amino acids in optimal combinations.
Milk and dairy products are considered nearly ideal sources of nutrients, especially protein and calcium, for pregnant or lactating women.
Ingestion of specific fish and potential methylmercury toxicity
are discussed later (p. 188).
# Minerals.
The intakes recommended by the Institute of Medicine (2006) for various minerals are listed in Table 10-5.
With the exception of iron and iodine, practically all diets that supply sufficient calories for appropriate weight gain will contain enough minerals to prevent deficiency.
Iron requirements substantively rise during pregnancy, and reasons for this are discussed in Chapter 4 (p. 60).
Of the approximately 300 mg of iron transferred to the fetus and placenta and the 500 mg incorporated into the expanding maternal hemoglobin mass, nearly all is used after midpregnancy.
During that time, iron requirements imposed by pregnancy and maternal excretion total approximately 7 mg/d .
Few women have sufficient iron stores or dietary intake to supply this amount.
Thus, the American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) endorse the recommendation by the National Academy of Sciences that at least 27 mg of elemental iron be supplemented daily to pregnant women.
This amount is contained in most prenatal vitamins.
As little as 30 mg of elemental iron, supplied as ferrous gluconate, sulfate, or fumarate, and taken daily throughout the latter half of pregnancy, provides sufficient iron to meet pregnancy requirements and protect preexisting iron stores .
This amount will also provide for iron requirements of lactation.
Notably, in iron preparations, the number of milligrams of compound is followed by the milligrams of elemental iron, which is enclosed by parentheses.
The pregnant woman may benefit from 60 to 100 mg of elemental iron per day if she is obese, has a multifetal gestation, begins supplementation late in pregnancy, takes iron irregularly, or has a depressed hemoglobin level.
The woman who is overtly anemic from iron deficiency responds well to oral supplementation with iron salts.
In response, serum ferritin levels rise more than the hemoglobin concentration .
Iodine also is needed, and the recommended iodine allowance is 220 µg/d .
The use of iodized salt and bread products is recommended during pregnancy to offset the increased fetal requirements and maternal renal losses of iodine.
Despite this, iodine intake has declined substantially in the past 15 years, and in some areas it is probably inadequate (Caldwell, 2013; Chittimoju, 2019).
Severe maternal iodine deficiency predisposes offspring to endemic cretinism, which is characterized by multiple severe neurological defects.
In parts of China and Africa, where this condition is common, iodide supplementation very early in pregnancy prevents some cretinism cases .
To obviate this, most prenatal supplements now contain various quantities of iodine .
Calcium is retained by the pregnant woman during gestation and approximates 30 g.
Most of this is deposited in the fetus late in pregnancy .
This amount of calcium represents only approximately 2.5 percent of total maternal calcium, most of which is in bone and can readily be mobilized for fetal growth.
As another potential use, routine calcium supplementation to prevent preeclampsia is ineffective .
Zinc deficiency if severe may lead to poor appetite, suboptimal growth, and impaired wound healing.
During pregnancy, the recommended daily intake approximates 12 mg.
But, the safe level of zinc supplementation for pregnant women is not clearly established.
Vegetarians have lower zinc intakes .
The bulk of studies support zinc supplementation only in zinc-deficient women in poor-resource countries (Nossier, 2015; Ota, 2015).
Magnesium deficiency as a consequence of pregnancy has not been recognized.
Undoubtedly, during prolonged illness with no magnesium intake, the plasma level might become critically low, as it would in the absence of pregnancy.
We have observed this deficiency during pregnancies in some with previous intestinal bypass surgery.
Instead, as a preventive agent, Sibai and colleagues (1989) randomly assigned 400 normotensive primigravidas to receive 365-mg elemental magnesium supplementation or placebo tablets from 13 to 24
weeks’ gestation.
Supplementation did not improve any measures of pregnancy outcome.
Trace metals include copper, selenium, chromium, and manganese, which all have important roles in certain enzyme functions.
In general, most are provided by an average diet.
Selenium deficiency is manifested by a frequently fatal cardiomyopathy in young children and reproductive-aged women.
Conversely, selenium toxicity resulting from oversupplementation also has been observed.
Selenium supplementation is not needed in American women.
Potassium concentrations in maternal plasma decline by approximately 0.5 mEq/L by midpregnancy .
Potassium deficiency develops in the same circumstances as in nonpregnant individuals.
One common example in pregnant women is hyperemesis gravidarum.
Fluoride metabolism is not altered appreciably during pregnancy .
Horowitz and Heifetz (1967) concluded that no additional offspring benefits accrued from maternal ingestion of fluoridated water if the newborn ingested such water from birth.
Sa Roriz Fonteles and associates (2005) studied microdrill biopsies of deciduous teeth and concluded that antenatal fluoride provided no additional fluoride uptake compared with postnatal fluoride alone.
Finally, supplemental fluoride ingested by lactating women does not raise the fluoride concentration in breast milk .
# Vitamins.
The increased requirements for most vitamins during pregnancy shown in Table 10-5.
usually are supplied by any general diet that provides adequate calories and protein.
The exception is folic acid during times of unusual requirements, such as pregnancy complicated by protracted vomiting, hemolytic anemia, or multiple fetuses.
That said, in impoverished countries, routine multivitamin supplementation reduced the incidence of lowbirthweight and growth-restricted fetuses but did not alter preterm delivery or perinatal mortality rates .
Folic acid supplementation in early pregnancy can lower neural-tube defect risks .
For example, the CDC (2004) estimated that the number of affected pregnancies had decreased from 4000 per year to approximately 3000 per year after mandatory fortification of cereal products with folic acid in 1998.
Perhaps more than half of all neural-tube defects can be prevented with daily intake of 400 µg of folic acid throughout the periconceptional period .
Evidence also suggests that folate insufficiency has a global effect on brain development .
Putting 140 µg of folic acid into each 100 g of grain products may increase the folic acid intake of the average American woman of childbearing age by 100 µg/d.
Because nutritional sources alone are insufficient, however, folic acid supplementation is still recommended.
A woman with a prior child with a neural-tube defect can reduce the 2to 5-percent recurrence risk by more than 70 percent with a daily 4-mg folic acid supplement taken during the month before conception and during the first trimester.
As emphasized by the American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017), this dose should be consumed as a separate supplement and not as multivitamin tablets.
This practice avoids excessive intake of fat-soluble vitamins.
Vitamin A, although essential, has been associated with congenital malformations when taken during pregnancy in high doses (>10,000 IU/d).
These malformations are similar to those produced by the vitamin A derivative isotretinoin (Accutane), which is a potent teratogen .
Beta-carotene, the precursor of vitamin A found in fruits and vegetables, does not produce vitamin A toxicity.
Most prenatal vitamins contain vitamin A in doses considerably below the teratogenic threshold.
Dietary intake of vitamin A in the United States appears to be adequate, and additional supplementation is not routinely recommended.
In contrast, vitamin A deficiency is an endemic nutritional problem in the developing world .
Vitamin A deficiency, whether overt or subclinical, is associated with night blindness and with an increased risk of maternal anemia and spontaneous preterm birth .
Vitamin
B12 plasma levels drop in normal pregnancy, mostly as a result of reduced plasma levels of their carrier proteins—transcobalamins.
Vitamin B12 occurs naturally only in foods of animal origin, and strict vegetarians may give birth to neonates whose B12 stores are low.
Likewise, because breast milk of a vegetarian mother contains little vitamin B12, the deficiency may become profound in the breastfed infant .
Excessive ingestion of vitamin C also can lead to a functional deficiency of vitamin B12.
Although its role is still controversial, vitamin B12 deficiency may be an independent factor associated with neural-tube defects .
Vitamin B6, which is pyridoxine, does not require supplementation in most gravidas .
For women at high risk for inadequate nutrition, a daily 2-mg supplement is recommended.
As discussed on page 191, vitamin B6, when combined with the antihistamine doxylamine, is helpful in many cases of nausea and vomiting of pregnancy.
Vitamin C allowances during pregnancy are 80 to 85 mg/d— approximately 20 percent more than when nonpregnant .
A reasonable diet should readily provide this amount, and supplementation is unnecessary .
Maternal plasma levels decline during pregnancy, whereas cord blood levels are higher.
This is a phenomenon observed with most water-soluble vitamins.
Vitamin D is a fat-soluble vitamin.
After being metabolized to its active form, it boosts the efficiency of intestinal calcium absorption and promotes bone mineralization and growth.
Unlike most vitamins that are obtained exclusively from dietary intake, vitamin D is also synthesized endogenously with exposure to sunlight.
Vitamin D deficiency is common during pregnancy.
This is especially true in high-risk groups such as women with limited sun exposure, vegetarians, and ethnic minorities—particularly those with darker skin .
Maternal deficiency can cause disordered skeletal homeostasis, congenital rickets, and fractures in the newborn .
However, vitamin D supplementation in women with asthma may decrease the likelihood of childhood asthma in their offspring .
The Food and Nutrition Board of the Institute of Medicine (2011) established that an adequate intake of vitamin D during pregnancy and lactation was 15 µg/d (600 IU/d).
In women suspected of having vitamin D deficiency, serum levels of 25hydroxyvitamin D can be obtained.
Even then, the optimal levels in pregnancy have not been established .
# Pragmatic Nutritional Surveillance.
Although researchers continue to study the ideal nutritional regimen for the pregnant woman and her fetus, basic tenets for the clinician include: 1. Advise the pregnant woman to eat food types she wants in reasonable amounts and salted to taste.
2. Ensure that food is amply available for socioeconomically deprived women.
3. Monitor weight gain and align goals with the Institute of Medicine recommendations.
4. Explore food intake by dietary recall periodically to discover the occasional nutritionally errant diet.
5. Give tablets of simple iron salts that provide at least 30 mg of elemental iron daily.
Give folate supplementation before and in the early weeks of pregnancy.
Provide iodine supplementation in areas of known dietary insufficiency.
6. Recheck the hematocrit or hemoglobin concentration at 28 to 32 weeks’ gestation to detect significant anemia.
Common Concerns.
# Employment.
More than half of the children in the United States are born to working mothers.
Several federal laws have been passed to protect pregnant workers.
These prohibit employers from excluding women from job categories on the basis that they are or might become pregnant.
The Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 requires that covered employers must grant up to 12 work weeks of unpaid leave to an employee for the birth and care of a newborn child.
In the absence of complications, most women can continue to work until labor onset .
Some types of work, however, may increase pregnancy complication risks.
According to the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018b), risks of preterm birth are slightly to modestly
increased with standing or walking at work >3 hours daily, lifting and carrying >5 kg, or physically exerting oneself at work.
In a prospective study of more than 900 healthy nulliparas, women who worked had a fivefold higher risk of preeclampsia .
Thus, any occupation that subjects the gravida to severe physical strain should be avoided.
Ideally, no work or play is continued to the extent that undue fatigue develops.
Adequate periods of rest should be provided.
# Exercise.
In general, pregnant women do not need to limit exercise, provided they do not become excessively fatigued or risk injury .
Clapp and associates (2000) reported that both placental size and birthweight were significantly greater in women who exercised.
Duncombe and coworkers (2006) reported similar findings in 148 women.
In contrast, Magann and colleagues (2002) prospectively analyzed exercise behavior in 750 healthy women and found that working women who exercised had smaller neonates and more dysfunctional labors.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) advises a thorough clinical evaluation before recommending an exercise program.
In the absence of contraindications listed in Table 10-6, pregnant women are encouraged to engage in regular, moderate-intensity physical activity for at least 150 minutes each week.
Such activity has been shown to not adversely alter uterine artery Doppler studies .
Each activity should be reviewed individually for its potential risk.
Examples of safe activities are walking, running, swimming, stationary cycling, and lowimpact aerobics.
However, they should refrain from activities with a high risk of falling or abdominal trauma.
Similarly, scuba diving is avoided because the fetus is at increased risk for decompression sickness .
Table 10-6.
Some Contraindications to Exercise During Pregnancy In the setting of certain pregnancy complications, it is wise to abstain from exercise and even limit physical activity.
Some women with pregnancyassociated hypertensive disorders, preterm labor, placenta previa, or severe cardiac or pulmonary disease may accrue advantages from being sedentary.
Also, those with multiple or suspected growth-restricted fetuses may be served by greater rest.
# Seafood Consumption.
Fish are an excellent source of protein, are low in saturated fats, and contain omega-3 fatty acids.
It is recommended that pregnant women ingest 8 to 12 ounces of fish weekly, but no more than 6 ounces of albacore or “white” tuna (U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, 2019).
Because nearly all fish and shellfish contain trace amounts of mercury, pregnant and lactating women are advised to avoid specific types of fish with potentially high methylmercury levels.
These include shark, swordfish, king mackerel, and tile fish.
If the mercury content of locally caught fish is unknown, overall fish consumption should be limited to 6 ounces per week.
Finally, to help avert listeriosis, eating raw or undercooked fish is avoided .
# Lead Screening.
Maternal lead exposure is associated with several adverse maternal and fetal outcomes across a range of maternal blood lead levels .
These include gestational hypertension, miscarriage, low birthweight, and neurodevelopmental impairments in exposed pregnancies.
The levels at which these risks rise remains unclear.
However, recognizing that such exposure remains a significant health issue for reproductive-aged women, the CDC (2010a) provides guidance for screening and managing exposed pregnant and lactating women.
These guidelines, which have been endorsed by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018f), recommend blood lead testing only if a risk factor is identified.
If the levels are >5 µg/dL, the lead source is sought and removed.
Subsequent blood levels are obtained.
Blood lead levels >45 µg/dL are consistent with lead poisoning, and women in this group may be candidates for chelation therapy.
Affected pregnancies are best managed in consultation with lead poisoning treatment experts.
National and state resources are
available at the CDC website: www.cdc.gov/nceh/lead/.
# Automobile and Air Travel.
Pregnant women are encouraged to wear properly positioned three-point restraints as protection against automobile accident injury .
The lap portion of the restraining belt is placed under the abdomen and across her upper thighs.
The belt should be comfortably snug.
The shoulder belt also is firmly positioned between the breasts.
Airbags should not be disabled for the pregnant woman.
In general, air travel in a properly pressurized aircraft has no harmful effect on pregnancy.
Thus, in the absence of obstetrical or medical complications, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018a) has concluded that pregnant women can safely fly up to 36 weeks’ gestation.
It is recommended that they observe the same precautions for air travel as the general population.
Seatbelts are used while seated.
Support stockings, periodic lower extremity movement, and at least hourly ambulation help lower the venous thromboembolism threat.
Significant risks with travel, especially international travel, are infectious disease acquisition and development of complications remote from adequate health-care resources.
# Coitus.
In healthy pregnant women, sexual intercourse usually is not harmful.
Whenever miscarriage, placenta previa, or preterm labor threatens, however, coitus is avoided.
Nearly 10,000 women enrolled in a prospective investigation by the Vaginal Infection and Prematurity Study Group were interviewed regarding sexual activity .
They reported a decreased frequency of coitus with advancing gestation.
By 36 weeks, 72 percent had intercourse less than once weekly.
The decline is attributed to lower desire and fear of harming the pregnancy .
Intercourse specifically late in pregnancy is not harmful.
Sayle and colleagues (2001) reported no increased—and actually a decreased—risk of delivery within 2 weeks of intercourse.
Tan and associates (2007) studied women scheduled for nonurgent labor induction and found that spontaneous labor ensued at equal rates in groups either participating in or abstaining from intercourse.
Oral-vaginal intercourse is occasionally hazardous.
Aronson and Nelson (1967) described a fatal air embolism late in pregnancy as a result of air blown into the vagina during cunnilingus.
Other near-fatal cases have been described .
# Dental Care.
Examination of the teeth is included in the prenatal examination, and good dental hygiene is encouraged.
Indeed, periodontal disease is linked to preterm labor.
Unfortunately, although its treatment improves dental health, it does not prevent preterm birth .
Dental caries are not aggravated by pregnancy.
Importantly, pregnancy is not a contraindication to dental treatment including dental radiographs .
# Immunization.
Current recommendations for immunization during pregnancy are summarized in Table 10-7.
Well-publicized concerns regarding a causal link between childhood exposure to the thimerosal preservative in some vaccines and neuropsychological disorders have led some parents to vaccine prohibition.
Although controversy continues, these associations have been proven groundless.
Thus, many vaccines may be used in pregnancy .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020c) stresses the importance of integrating an effective vaccine strategy into the care of both obstetrical and gynecological patients.
The College further emphasizes that information on the safety of vaccines given during pregnancy is subject to change, and recommendations can be found on the CDC website at www.cdc.gov/vaccines.
Table 10-7.
Recommendations for Immunization During Pregnancy and Postpartum Influenza and tetanus–diphtheria–acellular pertussis (Tdap) vaccinations are recommended routinely for all pregnant women (Munoz, 2019; Sperling, 2018b).
Others are recommended for specific indications .
Women who are susceptible to rubella should receive measles, mumps, and rubella (MMR) vaccination postpartum.
This vaccine is contraindicated during pregnancy.
# Caffeine.
Whether adverse
pregnancy outcomes are related to caffeine consumption is somewhat controversial.
As summarized from Chapter 11 (p. 200), heavy intake of coffee each day—approximately five cups or 500 mg of caffeine— slightly raises the miscarriage risk.
Studies of “moderate” intake—less than 200 mg daily—did not find a higher risk.
It is unclear if caffeine consumption is associated with preterm birth or impaired fetal growth.
Clausson and coworkers (2002) found no association between caffeine consumption <500 mg/d and low birthweight, fetal-growth restriction, or preterm delivery.
Bech and associates (2007) randomly assigned more than 1200 pregnant women who drank at least three cups of coffee per day to caffeinated versus decaffeinated coffee.
They found no difference in birthweight or gestational age at delivery between groups.
The CARE Study Group (2008), however, evaluated 2635 low-risk pregnancies and reported a 1.4-fold risk for fetal-growth restriction among those whose daily caffeine consumption was >200 mg/d compared with those who consumed <100 mg/d.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018g) concludes that moderate consumption of caffeine— less than 200 mg/d—does not appear to be associated with miscarriage or preterm birth, but that the relationship between caffeine consumption and fetal-growth restriction remains unsettled.
# Nausea and Heartburn.
Nausea and vomiting are common complaints during the first half of pregnancy.
These vary in severity and usually commence between the first and second missed menstrual period and continue until 14 to 16 weeks’ gestation.
Although nausea and vomiting tend to be worse in the morning— thus termed morning sickness—both symptoms frequently continue throughout the day.
Lacroix and associates (2000) found that nausea and vomiting were reported by three fourths of pregnant women and lasted an average of 35 days.
Half had relief by 14 weeks’ gestation, and 90 percent by 22 weeks’ gestation.
In 80 percent of these women, nausea lasted all day.
Treatment of pregnancy-associated nausea and vomiting seldom provides complete relief, but symptoms can be minimized.
Eating small meals at frequent intervals is valuable.
One systematic literature search reported that the herbal remedy ginger was likely effective .
Mild symptoms usually respond to vitamin B6 given with doxylamine, but some women require phenothiazine or H1-receptor blocking antiemetics .
In some with hyperemesis gravidarum, vomiting is so severe that dehydration, electrolyte and acid-base disturbances, and starvation ketosis become serious problems .
Heartburn is another common complaint of gravidas and is caused by gastric content reflux into the lower esophagus.
The greater frequency of regurgitation during pregnancy most likely results from upward displacement and compression of the stomach by the uterus, combined with relaxation of the lower esophageal sphincter.
Avoiding bending over or lying flat can be preventive.
In most pregnant women, symptoms are mild and relieved by a regimen of more frequent but smaller meals.
Antacids may provide considerable relief .
Specifically, aluminum hydroxide, magnesium trisilicate, or magnesium hydroxide are given alone or in combination.
Management of heartburn or nausea that does not respond to simple measures is discussed in Chapter 57 (p. 1017).
# Pica and Ptyalism.
The craving for strange foods is termed pica.
Worldwide, its prevalence among pregnant women is estimated to be 30 percent .
At times, nonfoods such as ice (pagophagia), starch (amylophagia), or clay (geophagia) may predominate.
This desire is considered by some to be triggered by severe iron deficiency .
Although such cravings usually abate after deficiency correction, not all pregnant women with pica are iron deficient.
Indeed, if strange “foods” dominate the diet, iron deficiency will be aggravated or will develop eventually.
Patel and colleagues (2004) prospectively completed a dietary inventory on more than 3000 women during the second trimester.
The prevalence
of pica was 4 percent.
The most common nonfood items ingested were starch in 64 percent, dirt in 14 percent, sourdough in 9 percent, and ice in 5 percent.
Women during pregnancy are occasionally distressed by profuse salivation—ptyalism.
Although usually unexplained, ptyalism sometimes appears to follow salivary gland stimulation by the ingestion of starch.
It commonly occurs with hyperemesis gravidarum .
# Headache or Backache.
Headaches are common in pregnancy.
At least 5 percent of pregnancies are estimated to be complicated by new-onset or new-type headache .
Acetaminophen is suitable for treatment of most, and an in-depth discussion is found in Chapter 63 (p. 1127).
Low back pain to some extent is reported by nearly 70 percent of gravidas .
Minor degrees follow excessive strain or significant bending, lifting, or walking.
It can be reduced by squatting rather than bending when reaching down, by using a back-support pillow when sitting, and by avoiding high-heeled shoes.
Back pain complaints increase with progressing gestation and are more prevalent in obese women and those with a history of low back pain.
In some cases, troublesome pain may persist for years after the pregnancy (Norén, 2002).
Severe back pain should not be attributed simply to pregnancy until a thorough orthopedic examination has been conducted.
Severe pain has other uncommon causes that include pregnancy-associated osteoporosis, disc disease, vertebral osteoarthritis, or septic arthritis .
More commonly, muscular spasm and tenderness are classified clinically as acute strain or fibrositis.
Although evidence-based clinical research directing care in pregnancy is limited, low back pain usually responds well to analgesics, heat, and rest.
Acetaminophen may be used as needed.
Nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs also may be beneficial but are used only in short courses to avoid fetal effects .
Muscle relaxants that include cyclobenzaprine or baclofen may be added when needed.
Once acute pain is improved, stabilizing and strengthening exercises provided by physical therapy help improve spine and hip stability, which is essential for the increased load of pregnancy.
For some, a support belt that stabilizes the sacroiliac joint may be helpful .
# Varicosities and Hemorrhoids.
Venous leg varicosities have a congenital predisposition and accrue with advancing age.
They can be aggravated by factors that raise lower-extremity venous pressures, such as an enlarging uterus.
Femoral venous pressures in the supine gravida rise from 8 mm Hg in early pregnancy to 24 mm Hg at term.
Thus, leg varicosities typically worsen as pregnancy advances, especially with prolonged standing.
Symptoms vary from cosmetic blemishes and mild discomfort at the end of the day to severe discomfort that requires prolonged rest with feet elevation.
Treatment is generally limited to periodic rest with leg elevation, elastic stockings, or both.
Surgical correction during pregnancy generally is not advised, although rarely the symptoms may be so severe that injection, ligation, or even stripping of the veins is necessary.
Superficial varicosities are a risk factor for deep-vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism .
Vulvar varicosities frequently coexist with leg varicosities, but they may appear without other venous pathology.
Uncommonly, they become massive and almost incapacitating .
If these large varicosities rupture, either spontaneously or at the time of delivery, blood loss can be severe.
Treatment is with specially fitted pantyhose that will also minimize lower extremity varicosities.
With particularly bothersome vulvar varicosities, a foam rubber pad suspended across the vulva by a belt can be used to exert pressure on the dilated veins.
Hemorrhoids are rectal vein varicosities and may first appear during pregnancy as pelvic venous pressures rise.
Commonly, they are recurrences of previously encountered hemorrhoids.
Up to 40 percent of pregnant women develop these .
Pain and swelling usually are relieved by topically applied anesthetics, warm soaks, and stool-softening agents.
With thrombosis of an external hemorrhoid, pain can be considerable.
This may be relieved by incision and removal of the clot following injection of a local anesthetic.
# Sleeping and Fatigue.
Beginning early in pregnancy, many women experience fatigue and need greater amounts of sleep.
The soporific effect of progesterone contributes but may be compounded in the first trimester by nausea and vomiting.
In the latter stages, general discomforts, urinary frequency, and dyspnea can be additive.
Sleep-disordered breathing may be associated with significant morbidities such as hypertensive disorders of pregnancy, stillbirth, and preterm delivery (Brown, 2018; Dominguez, 2018).
Moreover, sleep efficiency appears to progressively diminish as pregnancy advances.
Wilson and associates (2011) performed overnight polysomnography and observed that women in the third trimester had poorer sleep efficiency, more awakenings, and less of both stage 4 (deep) and rapid-eye-movement sleep.
Women in the first trimester also were affected, but to a lesser extent.
Daytime naps and mild sedatives at bedtime such as diphenhydramine (Benadryl) can be helpful.
# Cord Blood Banking.
Cord blood contains hemopoietic stem cells that can be used to treat more than 70 types of diseases.
These include immunological and genetic diseases and some forms of cancer.
Of the two cord blood bank types, public banks promote allogeneic donation, for use by a related or unrelated recipient, similar to blood product donation.
Private banks store stem cells for future autologous use and charge fees for initial processing and annual storage.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020e) has concluded that if a woman requests data on umbilical cord banking, information regarding advantages and disadvantages of public versus private banking should be explained.
Some states have passed laws that require physicians to inform patients about cord blood banking options.
Importantly, few transplants have been performed by using cord blood stored in the absence of a known indication in the recipient .
The likelihood that cord blood would be used for the child or family member of the donor couple is considered remote.
Instead, it is recommended that directed donation be considered when an immediate family member carries the diagnosis of a specific condition known to be treatable by hemopoietic transplantation.